was in mastering the CIA's writing
style. So, the most important product
that the CIA writes every day is the
PDB, the president's daily brief,
>> and it tells the president what
>> what you think he needs to know.
>> Okay?
>> So, for example, when the Iraqis began
moving to the to the Kuwaiti border,
we had this big debate. Are they going
to are they going to cross the border?
Yes or no? So I said, "Listen, why don't
I call the American Defense ATES in
Baghdad and I'll just ask him to drive
down there and look and tell us what he
sees?" He drives down there, drives
back, he calls me, and he says,
"Literally, the entire Iraqi military is
on its way to the Kuwaiti border." So we
wrote a thing for the president saying
Iraq is going to invade Kuwait and it's
probably going to happen in the next 48
hours. And when when did the president
see that particular briefing?
>> At 7:00 a.m. the next morning.
>> Okay. And is there ever situations where
the president would get it? In the
middle of the night.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah.
>> And be told in the middle of the night
that
>> Yes. There there are these levels of
immediacy.
There's routine, which is like who
cares? And then there is um priority,
which means ah I'll get to it sometime
today. Then there's immediate, which
means you should probably read it first.
But then there's flash,
which means, "Oh my god, something
terrible just happened. You should
probably wake the president." And then
there's critic, which means they're
coming over the embassy walls. We're at
war. Wake up the president. Scramble the
jets.
>> 911.
>> That's a critic.
[clears throat]
>> So going back to this question of your
training.
>> Yeah. What is it that the
CIA teach you about human nature and how
to use human nature to your advantage
that could be transferable to other
disciplines in life like business or
well this is going to sound
not very nice but it's it's real life
it's everyday life especially in in
business the CIA actively seeks to hire
people who have what they call
sociopathic tendencies.
Not sociopaths. Sociopaths have no
conscience. They'll just blow right
through a polygraph exam, but they're
impossible to corral. They're impossible
to to, you know, keep
under rain. Uh, and it's because they're
not able, their brains won't allow them
to feel regret or remorse. Now, in
business, most CEOs are sociopaths.
Most, not all, but most. Especially in
big companies, because they claw their
way to the top, usually on the backs of
the people around them. They don't feel
bad screwing the next guy to get that
next promotion. The CIA wants people
like that because those are the people
who are going to break into a foreign
embassy. A normal person would not
advocate breaking into a foreign
embassy. It's sovereign territory of a
foreign country. I would I'd be glad to
do it.
>> Why?
>> Because we're the good guys.
>> So, do you have sociopathic tendencies?
>> Absolutely.
>> And what are your sociopathic
tendencies?
>> My sociopathic tendency was to operate
in legal, moral, and ethical gray areas.
Specifically, that's what it was. I'm
really curious about what we can learn
about human nature from someone whose
job was to meet strangers and to get
them to basically sometimes to turn
against their own country.
>> Like I'm really interested in and I
think I think it's informative because
so many of us, you know, when we think
about what good leadership is or what
good sales man or womanship is,
>> um it seems like there's transferables.
I guess for some people it's family. I
guess for some people it's something
else that that that hook that you're
talking about, that thing that gets
them.
>> And the word that they use at the CIA
for the hook is a vulnerability. And
it's not really a vulnerability in every
case. Now,
95%
studies have been done about this
internally at the CIA. 95% of the people
who agree to become spies for us do it
for the money. Right? It's it's a simple
cash transaction. You give me money,
I'll give you secrets. 95%.
>> So, you telling me that you think human
motivation is 95% driven by money?
>> Yes.
>> Really?
>> Yes. The rest was love and family,
um, ideology,
revenge, and excitement.
You're going to get a handful of people
who are hooked on James Bond movies and
they will do it. I mean, you're going to
pay them anyway, but they will do it
just for the adrenaline rush.
>> It's interesting because when I look at
this list of things and I compare it to
business, it I would say it's slightly
different from my experience of hiring
people, specifically of hiring people. I
tend to think that, you know, you could,
one would ask themselves like, why would
someone leave a company right now like,
I don't know, Open AAI and go work at a
startup. They're going to get paid way
more at OpenAI. You've got these this
equity and these grants, but people are
on mass doing that. And even when I
think about the early days of Google,
people left the big conglomerates that
would pay them more
>> and they went and worked for Larry and
Sergey um getting paid way less, right?
but to be involved in something small,
scrappy, exciting,
>> and and so I and this is what what I
think about when I sit, you know,
probably I've had thousands of people in
my life now across my businesses, and
money is a factor, but it doesn't tend
to be the biggest factor.
[clears throat]
>> It tends to be, in my experience,
there's a particular hero's journey in
their mind that they want to be seen
through, they want to complete.
>> Uhhuh. you know, there's a particular
way that they see themselves and they
want to fulfill that.
>> Oh, I could get that. I I work with a
with a very very tiny startup right now
called Ivy Cyber and uh it it focuses on
privacy software, you know, things like,
you know, scrambling your data so it
can't be intercepted, that that sort of
thing. And
I've participated in a couple of pitches
to uh to angel investors
and they all say exactly the same thing
that you did.
>> And this is why I was confused when I
heard that money was 95%.
Because I I just think
especially in the work that you I don't
know especially in the work that you do.
I would assume
>> but look at it this way. I think this
would explain the discrepancy.
um you're comparing people who are
making a life
>> versus people who are betraying their
country.
>> True. And what's interesting as well is
in those examples that you've given,
money is actually a proxy to be able to
take care of my family.
>> Mhm.
>> And to be able to, you know, fulfill my
ideology and maybe to get excitement and
revenge. Do you know what I'm saying? So
even that guy that wanted the plane
ticket so he could fly home. Yeah. Yeah,
he could he could have the money could
have got him home if you just given him
>> the reason why he wanted to go home was
because his family
>> his family that was it.
>> What's the extent of the things that the
CIA can get as a incentive for someone
to turn against their nation to give
secrets?
>> Quite literally anything you can
imagine.
>> Even if it's against the law.
>> Well, like they're not going to get like
drugs or, you know, child prostitutes or
No, not stuff like that. What if someone
said, "I want you to
um
get me a a green card."
>> Oh, yeah, sure.
>> What if they said,
>> "If the information is good enough, not
a problem."
>> What if they said, "I want you to I've
got this tax bill. I want you to make
the tax bill go away."
>> Okay. Give me Give me the plans to that
Russian tank. We'll make it happen.
>> What if it was an American? Would they
speak to the IRS here and just get rid
of it?
>> Oh, if it was an American citizen, you
mean? Yeah.
>> Uh, no.
>> But they Why?
>> No.
We normally don't recruit American
citizens. By law, the CIA can't operate
domestically, although they have offices
all over the country. Those offices are
generally to to debrief business
leaders, seauite officers who travel to
denied areas. For example, if if you
take a trip to North Korea, let's say,
I'm going to call you and I'm going to
say, "You don't know me, but I'm from
the CIA, and I understand you just went
to North Korea, and I was wondering if I
could come over to your office for an
hour and just ask you about your trip."
99.99%
are going to say yes because they're
patriots. So, I go to your office, I
give you my business card, and we just
chat about, you know, your impressions
of the place and
that kind of thing.
>> Just to close off on this point, are
there any skills that the CIA taught you
or trained you in that you think are
transferable for business that we
haven't talked about?
>> They they trained us also in lying and
lie detection. That was actually quite
important. You know, you at the CIA,
you're you're a trained liar. And this
is why the divorce rate's so high. It's
the highest divorce rate of any uh
entity in in the US government. It's
it's upwards of 80%.
>> Trained to lie. How do they train you to
lie?
>> Hi, my name is Dave Phillips. U I work
for an import export company.
>> But do they teach you the art of lying?
>> Oh yeah.
>> And what is the art?
>> You know, it's it's hard to like it's
hard to pin down. You just sort of have
to have it. You have to have that
ability. But the hard part is you have
to keep the lies straight. I'll give you
another example. I've never told this
story before.
I was asked by headquarters. I was
overseas in the Middle East and I was
asked by headquarters to target one
specific officer of this foreign
country.
>> Target?
>> Yeah. Hi, how are you? Oh, we've never
met. I'm John. So nice to meet you. Let
me take you to lunch. he had access to
to information that we really needed. Uh
so they told me to accidentally bump
into him. So I surveiled him for a week
and he was single and on Saturday
morning he went to a coffee shop. So I
go into the coffee shop and I'm looking
at him and he's looking at me and I
said, "I know you, Ministry of Foreign
Affairs." He said, "Yes. Do I know you?"
I said, "I am John from the American
Embassy." "Oh, nice to nice to see you."
I said, 'Hey, good to see you, too. You
live in the area? Yes, I do. I said,
'Oh, so do I. I didn't. I lived like
across town. Oh, fancy meeting you here
at this coffee shop. I come here all the
time. Do you? Yeah, he says. I come here
all the time. Why don't you have a seat?
He says. So, I sit down. At the end of
the conversation, I go back to the
embassy and I read a cable and I said,
he's gay. I'm 100% sure he's gay. So,
then we started this conversation,
headquarters and I, how can we use that
to our benefit?
>> Did he have a wife?
>> No. He was single,
>> which was unusual at his age.
>> How did you know he was gay? [snorts]
>> Oh, I I just It was a vibe. Okay.
[laughter]
>> So,
headquarters says,
"We want you to pretend that you're
gay." I said, "Oh, come on, you guys.
No, we really need the information. You
got to pretend that you're gay." I said,
"Okay, I'll do it. I'll do it for Uncle
Sam."
So, I call him and I said, "Hey, I have
two tickets to this show and I was
hoping maybe you'd be free. Maybe we'll
grab some sushi afterwards."
He said, "Yeah, I'd love to." So, we go
to the show. He thoroughly enjoyed it
and we go for sushi afterwards and then
we go out again and he says, "Why don't
you come over to my place some night and
I'll I'll make dinner." I said, 'Great.'
So, I go over to his place. made a
lovely dinner and then I thought, well,
I have to invite him to my place. So, I
told my wife, you're going to have to
like get out. So, she left. I made
dinner. I removed all the pictures of us
together. And we had just gotten
married, so we had like our wedding
picture up and everything.
At the dinner,
he leaned in to kiss me and I
instinctively backed off and he said,
"Oh my god, I'm sorry. I thought you're
gay." And I said, "Oh, no. I I am gay.
I'm I'm I'm not into hairy guys.
And he's like, "Oh,
okay." I said, "I'm sorry. I think
you're great, but I'm I'm not feeling
it."
>> You didn't kiss him?
>> No. [laughter]
So, we remained friends and in the end,
he gave me the information because we
were friends. And then he he opened up.
He's like, "I can't tell anybody I'm
gay. They suspect I am." and they passed
me over for promotion. And my boss asked
me, "Is there something in your personal
life that you're not telling me? He
knows I'm gay." I said, "Listen, your
culture is backwards. Don't tell them
you're gay. Just say that you've just
never met the right woman." And
inshallah, the right woman is coming,
you know, in your life at some point.
And I actually Googled him a couple of
years ago, and he did become an
ambassador finally.
>> And he's still working in that country
now.
>> Mhm. Does that kind of stuff happen a
lot in the CIA where you have to take
one for the team?
>> Yes.
>> Have you ever taken one for the team?
>> No.
>> I'm not [laughter] sure you're telling
the truth.
>> Well, I it came close.
>> When did it come close?
>> So, I was overseas. I was a brand new
operations officer
and there was a woman in this foreign
intelligence service who was the ugliest
woman I've ever seen in my life.
Like you want to avert your eyes like
she came off the side of Notraam.
She was a, you know, a stone gargoyle
with a giant mole right here with a
giant hair coming out of it. That kind
of ugly.
So,
so I took her to lunch and she was very
nice. And then I thought I did something
kind of gutsy by C CIA standards because
it was early on in our relationship. I
invited her to go to lunch on a
Saturday. Now, as a rule, the people in
this country were not allowed to
socialize with us privately. It had to
be like their whole office, you know, or
several of them together. So, I asked
her just to meet me privately for lunch
on Saturday. Don't tell anybody.
>> So, she was someone from the Middle
East.
>> Yes. And she agreed. And I was like, "Oh
my god, she said yes." And I ran back to
the office. I was like, she said yes to
a lunch on Saturday alone. And my boss
says, "Okay, here's what I want you to
do. I want you to [__] her." And I said,
"What?" I said, "Have you ever seen
her?" And he said, "I know, but we're
the good guys, and you're going to have
to take one for the team." And I go, "Oh
my god." I said, I go,
"Okay, I'll do it." And he says, "No,
you're not going to [__] We don't do
that." I said, "I don't know. Oh, I just
started this. I've never been an
operations guy before. How am I supposed
to know? He said, "Come on." He said,
"Just develop her like a normal person.
You don't have to [__] her." I said, "Oh
my god, you almost gave me a heart
attack."
>> But they they might not be mad if you
did.
>> So long as I reported it and I got the
recruitment out of it.
>> It wasn't illegal to act, you know,
sleep with assets.
>> Yeah, you're not supposed to sleep with
assets. It has happened to a couple
people I know and um they end up being
pulled back to the United States. You
have to sit in the penalty box if you do
that. You're not supposed to do that.
But yeah, it happens sometime.
>> So sexion isn't a real thing.
>> It can be. We don't. [gasps]
[sighs]
When I first got hired, one of the
old-timers told me the story of about an
Ayatollah that they were trying to
recruit. And they set this Ayatollah up
with a prostitute. And it was he had sex
with this prostitute in a room where
they had cameras everywhere. And so they
bumped him afterwards. They bumped into
him and said, "Hey, we have all these
pictures." And they laid out the
pictures of him, you know, butt naked
with this prostitute. And he said,
"Yeah,
give me that one, an 8 by10. Give me two
5x7s of that one. How about some wallet
size for this?" He's like, "Get out of
here."
And he said, you know, after that, we
just stopped doing that. It doesn't
work. When you recruit somebody, you
really do need the relationship to be
based on mutual trust.